Register of the George E. Barantseff Collection
Hoover Institution Archives
George E. Barantseff collection,
1814-2001
2000C1
Barantseff, George E., collector
3 oversize boxes, 1 card file box (1.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Printed matter, photographs, memorabilia, and miscellany, relating to aspects of Russian imperial, military and émigré history.
Administrative Information
Access
Box 2 may not be used without permission of the Archivist.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Accruals
Increments may have been received since this finding aid was prepared. Please check Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat to find the full extent of the collection.
Scope and Content Note
The collection of Colonel Count George Barantseff consists mostly of printed matter and memorabilia related to Imperial Russia from Alexander II to Nicholas II and to the Russian emigration in China in the 1930s.
Of special interest are memorabilia belonging to the Barantseff family, including medals awarded to them by members of the imperial family.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Russia--History, Military.; Russians in foreign countries.; Russia--History.; Russia.
Container List
- Biographical File, 1999. (Box 1)
  Letter of appreciation
  - Letter of appreciation from the United States Coast Guard and miscellaneous printed matter re Alaska, 1999
- Writings, 1991. (Box 1)
  Essay re Romania
  - Barantseff, George, "A Current Major Issue in International Affairs: Romania," 1991.
    Typescript
- Printed Matter, 1814-1993. (Box 1)
  Books and periodicals related to the Russian imperial family, the Russian emigration in China, and Russian medals. Arranged alphabetically by physical form and therein by author
  - Books
    - V noch' na 17 iiulia 1918g., Izdanie detskago lageria imeni Tsesarevicha Vladimira, Tsingtao (Qingdao), 1936
    - Bozherianov, N., Trista Let Tsarstvovaniia Doma Romanovykh, Saint-Petersburg, 1912
    - Durov, V., Russkie i sovetskie boevye nagrady, Moscow, 1990
    - Moskovskii Otdel Obshchestva Popicheniia o Bednykh i Bol'nykh Detiakh, Al'bom-Knizhka Soderzhashchii Snimki iz Zhizni Naslednika Tsesarevicha i Velikago Kniazia Alekseia Nikolaevicha, Moscow, 1913
    - Nestor, Archbishop, Ocherki Dal'niago Vostoka, Belgrade, 1934
    - Nevskii, V., Vokrug Sveta Pod Russkim Flagom, Detgiz, 1953
    - Nikitina, V., Ordena Rossii, Moscow, 1991
    - Porter, Robert Ker, Narrative of the Campaign in Russia During the Year 1812, Hartford, 1814
    - Sheveleva, E., Nagrudnye Znaki Russkoi Armii, Saint-Petersburg, 1993
  - Periodicals
    - Pravoslavnaia Rus', San Francisco, 1978 July 17
    - Russkaia Zhizn', Jordanville, New York, 1968 July 17
- Miscellany, 1967. (Box 1)
  Defense Language Institute certificate of appreciation
  - Defense Language Institute certificate of appreciation awarded to George N. Markov, 1967
- Photographs, 1923-1994. (Box 1)
  Five prints related to the Russian imperial family, the Barantseff family, and the Russian emigration in China
  - 1 print depicting Count Evgenii Barantseff, 1923
  - 1 print depicting Colonel George Barantseff, 1994
  - 1 print depicting the Russian imperial family, n.d.
  - 1 print depicting Archbishop Nestor, 1934
  - 1 print depicting the White Russian Volunteer Force, Tientsin(?), China, 1930s(?)
- Memorabilia, 1901-1930s. (Box 2-3)
  Badges and medals related to Imperial Russia and the Russian emigration in China, pocket watch from the workshop of Pavel Bure, and Russian officer's sword. Arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Badges
    - Gold-colored badge, bearing the cipher of Empress Mariia Feodorovna, given to Countess Barantseff in recognition of her support for educational institutions under the empress's patronage, n.d.
    - 3 membership badges issued by colonial clubs in Tientsin, China, 1930s
  - Medals
    - Silver medal bearing the likeness of Emperor Alexander II, n.d.
      Remained in the possession of Count Barantseff and was never issued to the public
    - Silver medal bearing cipher of Emperor Nicholas II, awarded to combattants in the Boxer Rebellion, 1900-1901
    - Silver medal celebrating the tri-centennial of the Romanov dynasty, 1913
  - Pocket watch, n.d.
    Silver with gold plate initials from the workshop of Pavel Bure, watchmaker to the court of Nicholas II
  - Russian officer's sword, with pommel bearing the cipher of Emperor Nicholas II, n.d. (Box 3)
    The sword was broken in half so that Count Barantseff could smuggle it out of Russia and into Japan at the end of the Russian Civil War